Mss.Rec.73 Mss.Rec.73
American Philosophical Society
Quileute texts
1969
Mss.Rec.73
American Philosophical Society
5.0 Reel(s)
Linguistic field recordings of the Quileute language based on Manuel J. Andrade's (Columbia University Press, 1931), made by Eric Hamp. The recordings consist of Hamp reading back from Andrade's transcription of Quileute texts to Beatrice Black, a Quileute-speaking consultant, who repeats them in the correct pronunciation, provides explanation, and suggests corrections. Includes occasional discussions in English, with some infrequent English translations of the text. Texts included are primarily Quileute legends and folklore, with some speeches and descriptions of Quileute life, customs, and history. Recorded at Taholah, Washington, in August 1969.
5 sound tape reels (10 hr., 18 min.): analog, 3 3/4 ips, 2 track, mono; 7 in.
Andrade, Manuel José, 1885-1941
Black, Beatrice
Hamp, Eric P.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Eric Hamp in 1969. This material was recorded with the assistance of a Phillips Fund grant.
Indians of North America--Washington (State)--Olympic Peninsula; Quileute Indians--Fishing; Quileute Indians--Folklore; Quileute Indians--History; Quileute Indians--Social life and customs; Quileute language--Texts; Raven (Legendary character)--Legends; Sound recordings; Speeches, addresses, etc.
- Audio recordings
  - Text 1: What the Quileute do at present, 1969-08; 01-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:14:28; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
    Scope and Contents note
    This program consists of the researcher reading back a text in Quileute from Manuel J. Andrade's "Quileute Texts" (see Related Resource) to a Quileute-speaking consultant who assists in pronunciation, provides explanation, and suggests corrections. Interactions in English, with infrequent English translations of the text.
    Existence and Location of Originals note
    This file is a compressed, digitized version of the original. The APS Library maintains the original format (Sound tape reel) as well as an uncompressed digitized version of this recording.
    Quileute Indians--History; Quileute Indians--Social life and customs; Quileute language--Texts; Speeches, addresses, etc., Quileute; Taholah (Wash.)
  - Text 2: How a canoe is made, 1969-08; 01-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:36:07; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
    Canoes and canoeing--Design and construction; Quileute Indians--Material culture; Quileute language--Texts; Taholah (Wash.)
  - Text 3: How a fish-trap is made, 1969-08; 01-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:14:02; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
    Fish traps--Washington (State); Quileute Indians--Fishing; Quileute Indians--Material culture; Quileute language--Texts; Taholah (Wash.)
  - Quileute names for different kinds of salmon, 1969-08; 01-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:04; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
    Pacific salmon; Quileute Indians--Fishing; Quileute language; Taholah (Wash.)
  - Text 4: Do not spoil the country, 1969-08; 01-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:38:30; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
    Deforestation; Overfishing; Quileute Indians--History; Quileute language--Texts; Speeches, addresses, etc., Quileute; Taholah (Wash.)
  - Text 5: A potlatch speech [1 of 2], 1969-08; 01-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:28:08; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
    Potlatch--Washington (State); Quileute Indians--Social life and customs; Quileute language--Texts; Speeches, addresses, etc., Quileute; Taholah (Wash.)
  - Text 5: A potlatch speech [2 of 2], 1969-08; 02-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:26:42; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
  - Text 6: Raven uses his son for bait [1 of 2], 1969-08; 02-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:40:32; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
    Quileute Indians--Folklore; Quileute language--Texts; Raven (Legendary character)--Legends; Taholah (Wash.)
  - Text 6: Raven uses his son for bait [2 of 2], 1968-08-29; 02-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:04:06; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
  - Text 7: Raven is fooled, 1969-08; 02-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:18:13; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
  - Discussion of the closing of the beach due to recent vandalism, 1969-08; 02-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:04:46; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
    Beaches--Washington (State); Quileute language; Quinault Reservation (Wash.); Taholah (Wash.); Vandalism
  - Text 8: Raven's son married Mole's daughter, 1969-08; 02-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:39:33; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
    Moles (Animals)--Folklore; Quileute Indians--Folklore; Quileute language--Texts; Raven (Legendary character)--Legends; Taholah (Wash.)
  - Text 9: Raven kills deer [1 of 2], 1969-08; 02-07; 1.0 .mp3; 00:08:10; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
    Deer--Folklore; Quileute Indians--Folklore; Quileute language--Texts; Raven (Legendary character)--Legends; Taholah (Wash.)
  - Text 9: Raven kills deer [2 of 2], 1969-08; 03-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:19:00; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
    This program consists of the researcher reading back a text in Quileute from Manuel J. Andrade's "Quileute Texts" (see Related Resource) to a Quileute-speaking consultant who assists in pronunciation, provides explanation, and suggests corrections. Interactions in English, with infrequent English translations of the text. The section from 4:21 to 5:14 contains material in the Quinault language.
  - Text 10: Raven fools Crow, 1969-08; 03-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:32:34; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
    Crows--Folklore; Quileute Indians--Folklore; Quileute language--Texts; Raven (Legendary character)--Legends; Taholah (Wash.)
  - Text 11: Raven eats Goose's Children, 1969-08; 03-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:18:00; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
    Geese--Folklore; Quileute Indians--Folklore; Quileute language--Texts; Raven (Legendary character)--Legends; Taholah (Wash.)
  - Text 12: Goose revenges herself upon Raven [1 of 2], 1969-08; 03-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:25; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
  - Text 12: Goose revenges herself upon Raven [2 of 2], 1969-08; 03-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:18:15; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
  - Text 13: Raven visits Hair-seal, 1969-08; 03-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:15:47; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
    Quileute Indians--Folklore; Quileute language--Texts; Raven (Legendary character)--Legends; Seals (Animals)--Folklore; Taholah (Wash.)
  - Text 14: Raven visits Fish-duck [1 of 2], 1969-08; 03-07; 1.0 .mp3; 00:26:48; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
    Ducks--Folklore; Quileute Indians--Folklore; Quileute language--Texts; Raven (Legendary character)--Legends; Taholah (Wash.)
  - Text 14: Raven visits Fish-duck [2 of 2], 1969-08; 04-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:08:23; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
  - Text 15: Raven visits Bear, 1969-08; 04-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:34:39; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
    Bears--Folklore; Quileute Indians--Folklore; Quileute language--Texts; Raven (Legendary character)--Legends; Taholah (Wash.)
  - Text 16: Q'wäeti' and the man-eating whale, 1969-08; 04-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:14:31; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
    This program consists of the researcher reading back a text in Quileute from Manuel J. Andrade's "Quileute Texts" (see Related Resource) to a Quileute-speaking consultant who assists in pronunciation, provides explanation, and suggests corrections. Interactions in English, with infrequent English translations of the text. The program ends before the story is completed. There is a 3-second silent gap at 13:33.
    Quileute Indians--Folklore; Quileute language--Texts; Taholah (Wash.); Whales--Folklore
  - Text 17: Q'wäeti' and the wolves [1 of 3], 1969-08; 04-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:06:45; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
    This program consists of the researcher reading back a text in Quileute from Manuel J. Andrade's "Quileute Texts" (see Related Resource) to a Quileute-speaking consultant who assists in pronunciation, provides explanation, and suggests corrections. Interactions in English, with infrequent English translations of the text. The beginning of the story is not found on the original recording. This program begins approximately 8 lines after the story's beginning in the source text. The length of the entire story in the source text is 40 lines. The section from 5:30 through the end of the program contains material in the Makah language.
    Quileute Indians--Folklore; Quileute Indians--History; Quileute language--Texts; Taholah (Wash.); Wolves--Folklore
  - Text 17: Q'wäeti' and the wolves [2 of 3], 1969-08; 04-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:09:47; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
    This program consists of the researcher reading back a text in Quileute from Manuel J. Andrade's "Quileute Texts" (see Related Resource) to a Quileute-speaking consultant who assists in pronunciation, provides explanation, and suggests corrections. Interactions in English, with infrequent English translations of the text. The section from the beginning of the recording through 0:47 contains material in the Makah language.
  - Text 27: The origin of the tribes, 1969-08; 04-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:29:32; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
    Indians of North America--Washington (State)--Olympic Peninsula; Quileute Indians--Folklore; Quileute language--Texts; Taholah (Wash.)
  - Text 29: Q'wäeti' institutes privacy in marital relations, 1969-08; 04-07; 1.0 .mp3; 00:06:43; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
    Quileute Indians--Folklore; Quileute Indians--Social life and customs; Quileute language--Texts; Sexual intercourse; Taholah (Wash.)
  - Text 30: Q'wäeti'-'s amorous adventure [1 of 2], 1969-08; 04-08; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:50; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
    Dungeness Spit (Wash.); Quileute Indians--Folklore; Quileute language--Texts; Taholah (Wash.)
  - Text 30: Q'wäeti'-'s amorous adventure [2 of 2], 1969-08; 05-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:12:17; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
  - Text 17: Q'wäeti' and the wolves [3 of 3], 1969-08; 05-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:20:06; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
  - Discussion of Quileute place names, 1969-08; 05-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:06:40; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
    Indians of North America--Washington (State)--Olympic Peninsula; Names, Geographical--Washington (State)--Olympic Peninsula; Quileute language; Taholah (Wash.)
  - Text 18: Q'wäesti' deceives Dásk'iya' [1 of 2], 1969-08; 05-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:10:29; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
    Monsters--Folklore; Quileute Indians--Folklore; Quileute language--Texts; Taholah (Wash.)
  - Text 18: Q'wäesti' deceives Dásk'iya' [2 of 2], 1969-08; 05-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:07:21; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
  - Text 19: Dásk'iya' is killed by a girl, 1969-08; 05-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:22:31; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.
  - Text 20: Devil-fish kills Dásk'iya', 1969-08; 05-07; 1.0 .mp3; 00:17:59; Black, Beatrice; Hamp, Eric P.